A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor Andrew J. Montague, 1884-1907 (bulk 1902-1905)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Executive Papers of Governor Andrew J. Montague, 1884-1907 (bulk 1902-1905)
The Library of Virginia
22001, 23349, 45102
24.5 cubic feet (56 boxes)
Virginia. Governor (1902-1906: Montague)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These materials came in several accessions and were combined into one body of records under Acc. 45102. Included are the following accessions: Acc. 22001; 23349; & 45102.
Papers & Correspondence of Governor Andrew J. Montague. Gift of Elizabeth Hoskins Montague, 1942 Dec. 30 (22001).
Executive Papers, 1898-1902, 3,000 items. Transferred from the Governor's Office on 26 January 1947 (23349).
Biographical Information
Andrew Jackson Montague was born 3 October 1862 in Campbell County, Virginia. The son of Robert Latane Montague, lieutenant governor under John Letcher, and Cordelia Eubank, Andrew graduated from Richmond College in 1882 and from the University of Virginia law school in 1885. Montague entered private practice in Danville, Virginia, then was appointed by President Grover Cleveland as U.S. Attorney General for the Western District of Virginia in 1893. Montague later served as Attorney General of Virginia from 1898 to 1902. Montague defeated Republican candidate J. Hampton Hoge as governor of Virginia serving from 1902 to 1906. While in office, progressive-minded Montague promoted good roads and public schools. An opponent of fellow Democrat and incumbent senator Thomas Martin, Montague lost his bid as senatorial candidate in 1905. Following his governorship, Montague served as dean of the Richmond College law school from 1906 to 1909, and practiced law in Richmond, Virginia, from 1909 to 1913. Elected to the U.S. Congress in 1913, Montague served until his death on 24 January 1937 in Urbana, Virginia. He is buried in Christ Church Cemetery in Middlesex County, Virginia. Montague married Elizabeth Lyne Hoskins in 1889 and they had three children.
Scope and Content
Governor Andrew J. Montague Executive papers are organized in four series. Series have been designated for Correspondence (Chronological), Correspondence (Alphabetical), Letter Books, and Personal Papers. These papers mainly consist of incoming and outgoing correspondence during Andrew J. Montague's four-year term as governor between 1 January 1902 and 1 February 1906. The Correspondence (Chronological) series is the most important among Montague's Executive Papers documenting the chief correspondents and issues during Montague's governorship. The Personal Papers series is the largest and should be utilized along with the Correspondence (Chronological) series. This series contains additional significant correspondence. The Personal Papers series is not exclusively records of a personal nature, but contains materials in Montague's official capacity as governor. The Letter Books series contains the outgoing copies of correspondence sent by Governor Montague. Additional earlier letter books belonging to Montague can be found in Accession 22001 of Private Papers. Still more letter books comprising his years as governor can be found in the Library's Vault.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence (Chronological), 1902-1906
Series II. Correspondence (Alphabetical), 1884-1907
Series III. Letter Books, 1901-1906
Series IV. Personal Papers, 1895-1906
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Material
Oversized items have been removed to Boxes 54-55.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence (Chronological), 1902-1906., Extent: 15 boxes. (Box 1-15)
  The Correspondence (Chronological) series is housed in fifteen archival boxes and is arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by correspondent. This series documents correspondence received by Governor Montague and a small amount of outgoing correspondence that was returned. In addition to correspondence, there are reports, proclamations, telegrams, orders, resolutions, acts, publications, news clippings, invitations, proceedings, financial statements, invoices, and other sundry items. Correspondence in this series relates to appointments, extraditions, the Good Roads Convention, convicts & the Penitentiary, Executive Mansion & Capitol improvements, proclamations, state mental hospitals, the Virginia Volunteers, the Virginia Military Institute, pardons, Virginia State Library, and others. Noteworthy correspondents include William A. Anderson, Attorney General; George Helms, Superintendent of the Penitentiary; William F. Drewry, Superintendent of Central State Hospital; L.S. Foster, Superintendent of Eastern State Hospital; R.J. Preston, Superintendent of Southwestern State Hospital; John Hay, Secretary of State; William Nalle, Adjutant General; Scott Shipp, Superintendent of the Virginia Military Institute; and John P. Kennedy, State Librarian.
  Attorney General, William A. Anderson, writes to Governor Montague to provide opinions regarding a variety of issues. Anderson provides opinions on the following topics: the contract between the Superintendent of the Penitentiary and the Davis Boot & Shoe Company (1902 Feb. 15), the petition of H.G. Nutt (1902 Sept. 26), the Brickhouse suit (1903 Mar. 26), Judge Farrar's duties under Section 9 of the Virginia Election Law (1903 Oct. 20), the Walton-Parker Law (1903 Oct. 9), the nomination of Judge William A. Smith of the Cumberland County Court as Commonwealth's Attorney (1903 Oct. 20), the shooting of a horse by a South Carolina soldier (1904 Dec. 22), the reduction of the sentence to a convict in the Penitentiary (1904 Dec. 12), and Article XVI of the Convention between the U.S. & Italy (1905 Sept. 14).
  During Montague's term in office, he received correspondence & reports from both the superintendent & president of the Board of Directors of the Virginia Penitentiary. A.C. Harman & W.D. Chesterman, Presidents of the Board of Directors, submit synopses of the superintendent's & surgeon's monthly reports (1902 Jan. 7, Apr. 15, & July 7). Chesterman writes regarding the use of convicts to work on the road to Monticello (1902 Feb. 12). Chesterman's successor as president of the Board of Directors, Milton E. Marcuse, submits a surgeon's report (1903 May 5). Lastly, as superintendent, George M. Helms writes regarding the sanity of two convicts in the Penitentiary (1903 Oct. 26).
  Correspondence to Governor Montague also originates from the various superintendents & president of the Board of Directors of Virginia's state mental hospitals including Central State Hospital, Eastern State Hospital, & Southwestern State Hospital. William F. Drewry, Superintendent of Central State Hospital, submits quarterly reports to Governor Montague (1902 Jan. 8 & 1904 Apr. 7). Drewry also writes on 22 December 1905 enclosing the amount appropriated for the maintenance & improvements at the hospital. Robert Gilliam, President of the Board of Directors of Central State Hospital, encloses the superintendent's report for the quarter ending 31 December 1902 (1902 Oct. 8). L.S. Foster, Superintendent of Eastern State Hospital, provides a brief account of the fire which occurred at the Hospital on 4 January (1902 Feb. 10). In addition, John L. Mercer, clerk, encloses proceedings of the Board of Directors of Eastern State Hospital regarding the fire (1902 Jan. 8). R.J. Preston, Superintendent of Southwestern State Hospital, submits a census of patients, along with the Steward's financial statement (1902 Jan. 7 & 1904 May 4). Preston also writes regarding overcrowded conditions at the hospital (1902 July 15). Preston submits encloses quarterly reports on 1903 Jan. 7 & Apr. 7. On 19 July 1904, Preston writes regarding the movement of patients (admissions, discharges, etc.) & quarterly financial statement. In addition, John G. Osborne, President of the Board of Directors of the Southwestern State Hospital, advises the governor on state of the hospital (1902 Oct. 21).
  John Hay, Secretary of State, writes to Governor Montague regarding various issues. Hay writes regarding the extradition from Great Britain of a fugitive from justice (1902 Feb. 5). Hay also writes regarding the judgment of the Supreme Court of the U.S. in the fisheries case of Manchester vs. Massachusetts (1902 Feb. 10). In addition, Hay encloses Advance Sheets of Consular Reports, No. 1271 (1902 Mar. 4). On 27 March 1903, Hay writes regarding changes to the Imperial German marriage law. Finally, Hay writes regarding legislative regulative and protection of the sale of cheese (1903 Oct. 24).
  As Adjutant General, William Nalle writes concerning general & special orders, the Virginia Volunteers, and the return of Confederate battle flags. Nalle submits special orders regarding the uniform & equipment of the governor's staff (1902 Jan. 25 & 29). Nalle also submits general orders regarding an oath to maintain & support the new state constitution by all the members of the Virginia Volunteers (1902 June 28). On 20 April 1903, Nalle encloses a list of surgeons connected with the Virginia Volunteers. Additionally, Nalle writes regarding an act to promote the efficiency of the militia (1903 Sept. 29). On 26 October 1904, Nalle transmits General Court Martial proceedings. Lastly, Nalle, John Lamb, & J.L. Moring write regarding the examination of Confederate battle flags sent to Virginia by the Secretary of war (incl. letter of William H. Taft, Secretary of War & a list of the confederate flags) (1905 Mar. 28).
  Scott Shipp, Superintendent of the Virginia Military Institute, corresponds with Governor Montague regarding the discipline of cadets, typhoid fever, and cadet complaints. Included is a printed report of Shipp as superintendent to the Board of Visitors on a breach of discipline upon part of certain cadets (1902 Dec. 15). Shipp also includes a report regarding typhoid fever in Lexington (1903 Oct. 24). Later, Shipp writes regarding a leave of absence for cadets and the health conditions at VMI (1903 Nov. 16). Furthermore, Shipp writes regarding complaints by cadets about the food in the Mess Hall (1905 Nov. 13). Lastly, Shipp provides statistics on cadet discipline (1906 Jan. 3).
  John P. Kennedy, State Librarian, provides information regarding conditions at the Virginia State Library. On 31 March 1904, Kennedy writes regarding the resolution of the Library Board requesting the governor to turn over to the Virginia State Library any or all space shortly to be vacated by the Law Library (1904 Mar. 31). Kennedy also writes regarding the addition of more libraries, stack space, salary adjustments, and new positions including a Chief of the Reading Room, bibliographer, Chief of the Dept. of Archives & History, and Chief of the Serials Division (1905 Dec. 14).
  Additional miscellaneous correspondence includes the following: telegrams of John W. Crockett, Sheriff of Pocahontas, re. strikers from West Virginia coming to Pocahontas for the purpose of forcing the men to quit (1902 June 17 & 18); William Jennings Bryan, Lincoln, re. an amendment to the Constitution providing for the election of U.S. senators by direct vote of the people (1902 Feb. 6); Noland & Baskervill, Architects & Engineers, providing an estimate of proposed improvements at the Executive Mansion (1902 Mar. 4); A.H. Buchanan, Tennessee & Virginia Boundary Commission, encl. a statement of expenditures in the Boundary Survey (1902 Sept. 24); report of the president of the Richmond Chamber of Commerce (1902 Jan. 9); John W. Daniel, Senator from Virginia, re. the claims of Virginia against the U.S. (1902 Aug. 16); Martin Dodge, Director of the U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, encl. a bill to create a Bureau of Public Roads (1902 Dec. 11); D.Q. Eggleston, Secretary of the Commonwealth, encl. a resolution of the Tennessee General Assembly re. the calling of a convention to propose an amendment to the U.S. Constitution providing for the election of U.S. senators by direct vote of the people (1902 Apr. 3); convention between the U.S. & Guatemala re. the tenure & disposition of real & personal property (1902 Sept. 18); John R. Hooper, Superintendent of the Hollywood Cemetery Company, re. the removal of inscription plates on the tomb of President James Monroe by vandals (1902 Jan. 24); G.L. Hergert, Secretary of the American Exposition, encl. a plan of the main floor of the Crystal Palace in London (1902 Feb. 3); Giles B. Jackson, Secretary of the Negro Business League of Virginia, re. the annual meeting of the National League of the U.S. in Richmond (1902 Apr. 26); proclamation of Governor Charles B. Aycock, North Carolina, calling for a Good Roads Convention in Raleigh (1902 Jan. 22); Andrew J. Montague to the Senate & House of Delegates re. the fire at Eastern State Hospital, the condition of the Capitol Building, Penitentiary, etc. (1902 Feb. 20); proclamation of Governor Andrew J. Montague designating November 27, 1902, as a day of Thanksgiving (1902 Nov. 13); Ethan A. Hitchcock, Dept. of the Interior, transmitting a resolution of the Senate that the Secretary of the Interior & Secretary of Agriculture transmit to the Senate any facts on the buffalo or American bison (1902 Feb. 3); John W. Williams, Clerk of the House of Delegates, encl. a joint resolution that the governor be requested to invite plans & specifications for the renovation & repair of the exterior & interior of the Capitol (1902 Feb. 20); report of the Office of the Attorney General (1902 Nov.); W.P. Brownlow, Committee on Appropriations, House of Representatives, encl. H.R. 15369 providing for a system of national, state, & local cooperation in the permanent improvement of the public highways (1903 Mar. 4); Clara Barton, American National Red Cross, requesting the governor's membership on the National Advisory Board of the Red Cross (1903 July 18); Clara Barton re. the nomination of George B. Davis to represent Virginia in the National Advisory Board of the Red Cross (1903 Sept. 19); George C. Cabell, Jr., resigning as Chief of Staff (1903 Mar. 19); act of Congress to regulate the immigration of aliens into the U.S. (1903 Mar. 3); invitation to the Louisiana Purchase Centennial Dedication ceremonies in St. Louis (1903 May 2); Andrew A. Lipscomb, Chairman of the Board of Governors, Thomas Jefferson Memorial Association of the U.S., re. a memorial to the author of the Declaration of Independence at the National Capital (1903 May 14); Jefferson Myers, President of the Lewis & Clark Centennial Exposition Commission, inviting Virginia to make an exhibit at the Lewis & Clark Exposition to be held in Portsmouth in 1905 (1903 Dec. 12); Noland & Baskervill re. their bill for services in repairs to the Executive Mansion (1903 Jan. 22); William C. Ritter, President of the Virginia Association for the Deaf, re. the education of colored deaf & blind children (1903 Apr. 8); Frederick E. Rittman, Auditor, Treasury Dept., Office of the Auditor for the War Dept., re. expenses due Virginia for the benefit of the U.S. during the War of 1812 (1903 Apr. 22); Rittman re. expenses incurred by Virginia in aiding the U.S. to raise the volunteers army for the war with Spain (1903 June 8); Clara Barton re. the American National Red Cross and encl. booklet "Clara Barton & Her Work" & "The Red Cross on a New Field" (1903 June 10); proclamation of Governor Montague designating November 26, 1903, as Thanksgiving Day (1903 Nov. 11) (Acc. # 33675); Governor J.M. Terrell, Georgia, re. the National Conference of Charities & Corrections in Atlanta (1903 Mar. 23); R.J. Tracewell, Comptroller, Treasury Dept., re. the readjustment of all claims of the State of Virginia for & on account of advances & expenditures made by the state during the War of 1812 (1903 Feb. 5); Richard M. Taylor, Mayor of Richmond, requesting aid to restore peace & good order in the city (1903 June 23); William Cary Sanger, Assistant Secretary of War, re. inspections of the organized militia of the several states (1903 June 5); bill for the purchase & preservation of Jamestown Island, Virginia (H.R. 15439) (1904 Apr. 26); George H. Harries, Chairman of the Inaugural Committee, requesting information on the participation of Virginia troops in the parade following the inauguration of President Roosevelt (1904 Dec. 10); Giles B. Jackson, director of the Negro Development & Exposition Company of the U.S., encl. an address of the company (1904 July 14); Fitzhugh Lee, President of the Jamestown Exposition Company, re. selection of a date for "Virginia Day" (1904 Sept. 6); John W. Richardson, Register & Superintendent of Public Grounds & Buildings, encl. his opinion of William A. Anderson re. the heating of the State Library Building (1904 May 3); John G. Tilton, Attorney, protesting against the pardon of Annie Whaley, mother of Lillie Davis, who is serving a 12-month sentence in Norfolk City Jail for beating her daughter (incl. photograph of Davis with scars & bruises) (1904 Apr. 15); Booker T. Washington, Principal, encl. annual report of the Tuskegee Normal & Industrial Institute (1904 Nov. 5); Otto Eisenrohr encl. a photograph of Gilbert Stuart's portrait of Gen. George Washington and offering to see a reproduction (1904 [N.D.]); Mrs. L.L. Harman, Staunton, re. the establishment of a school for the colored deaf, dumb, & blind (letterhead incl. photo of Wheatland Farm) (1905 Nov. 22); G. Trentenove, Florence, Italy, re. payment for his marble sculpture of the late General Fitzhugh Lee in the rotunda of the Capitol (1905 May 20); Woodrow Wilson re. an account of the ceremonies attending his inauguration as President of Princeton University (1905 Mar. 21); specification & description of work & material required in the repairing & completion of work necessary to be done on the Governor's Mansion (1905 undated); Janet H. Randolph, President of the Fitzhugh Lee Monument Association, requesting an appropriation of $10,000 (1906 Jan. 24); and Claude A. Swanson resigning as a member of the House of Representatives (1906 Jan. 24).
  Arranged chronologically by year, then alphabetically by correspondent.
  - 1902
    - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - B
      - January-June (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - July-December (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - C
      - January-June (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - July-December (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - D (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - E (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - F (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - G (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - H
      - January-June (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - July-December (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - I (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - J (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - K (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - L (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - M
      - January-June (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - July-December (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - N (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - O (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - P
      - January-August (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - September-December (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Q (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - R (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - S
      - January-May (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - June-December (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - T (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - U (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - V (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - W
      - January-June (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - July-December (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Y (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Z (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Unsigned or Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1903
    - A (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - B
      - January-June (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - July-December (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - C
      - January-June (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - July-December (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - D (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - E (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - F (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - G (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - H (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - I (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - J (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - K (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - L (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - M
      - January-June (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - July-December (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - N (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - O (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - P (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Q (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - R (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - S
      - January-October (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - November-December (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - T (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - U (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - V (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - W
      - January-June (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - July-December (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Unsigned or Undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1904
    - A (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - B
      - January-June (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - July-December (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - C
      - January-June (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - July-December (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - D (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - E (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - F (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - G (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - H
      - January-August (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - September-December (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - I (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - J (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - K (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - L (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - M (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - N (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - O (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - P (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - R (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - S
      - January-June (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - July-December (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - T (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - U (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - V (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - W
      - January-June (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - July-December (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Unsigned or Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 1905
    - A (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - B
      - January-June (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - July-December (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - C (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - D (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - E (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - F (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - G (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - H
      - January-September (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - October-December (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - I (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - J (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - K (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - L
      - January-August (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - September-December (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - M
      - January-June (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - July-December (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - N (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - O (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - P (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - R (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - S
      - January-October (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - November-December (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - T (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - U (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - V (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - W
      - January-August (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - September-December (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Y (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Z (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Unsigned or Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - 1906
    - January
      - A-C (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - D-L (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - M-S (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - T-W (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - February (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Series II: Correspondence (Alphabetical), 1884-1907 (bulk 1902-1905)., Extent: 8 boxes. (Box 16-22a)
  The Correspondence (Alphabetical) series is housed in seven archival boxes and is arranged alphabetically by folder title. This series documents subject files maintained by Governor Andrew J. Montague. In addition to correspondence, there are reports, bills, receipts, recommendations, telegrams, lists, applications, pardons, proclamations, and other sundry items.